# **Bobby Estes**

# Senior Software & Python/AI/ML Engineer & MLOps Specialist

Florida, United State(US citizen)
bobbyestes.ai@gmail.com
https://bobby-linkedin-redirect.vercel.app/
https://bobby-estes.vercel.app/
+ 1 8 6 3 2 1 3 0 4 2 6

I am an ambitious Senior AI/ML Backend Engineer, with 10 years of experience in the Software Development industry.

My passion for Artificial Intelligence research and development ignited at its very beginning in America. Since then, I've been keen on architecting, designing, and implementing top-of-the-line software solutions tailored to the unique needs of businesses.

My commitment to staying at the forefront of technological advancements has enabled me to exceed the evolving demands of the digital business landscape.

My biggest differentiator is my expertise - based upon best practices study, a non-conventional approach that goes beyond the latest tech trends, and proven solutions that best fit business objectives. Whether we're talking about Product Development, driving projects as a Contractor, I'm enthusiastic about delivering results that transcend expectations.

My proficiency in AI, MLOps, and System Architecture are not just skill sets. They are components that bridge the gap between real-world solutions and advanced algorithmic strategies.

# - Technical Proficiencies

**Languages:** Python, JavaScript, C++, Rust

**Software Design** FTI Architecture, batch serving architecture, online real-time pipeline, offline batch

**Architecture:** pipeline, asyncronous inference pipeline

AI Frameworks: PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, Scikit-learn, XGBoost, langchain, Llama-index,

Haystack, langGraph, AutoGen, Crew AI, Agentic Transformer

MLOps GCP(Vertex AI, GCR, GKE, GCS, pub/sub), AWS(AWS SageMaker, Fargate, lambda,

S3 bucket), Azure, W&B, DVC, Arize, Comet ML, Qwak, Databricks, MLFlow, Apache

Spark

LLM: OpenAI, Anthropic, Azure, Llama-3, Mistral, Multi-modal LLM(TTS/STT/VST/AST),

SDXL, Gemini, Vertex, Perplexity, Advanced RAG, TAG, Advanced chunking strategy

**Data Science:** Pydantic, PySpark, Pandas, Polar, Ibis, BigQuery

Fullstack Development: Django, Flask, FastAPI, Express.JS, Node.js, PHP, React.JS, Next.JS

Database: PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Aurora DB, DynamoDB, Redis, Qdrant, SnowFlake,

Hopsworks, PGVector, Pinecone, Milvus

Orchestrator: Docker Swarm, ECS, K8s, Airflow, Kubeflow, ZenML, PipeDream

**ORM:** Alchemy, Peewee, Django ORM

**API Design Models:** REST API, RPC, GraphQL

CI/CD: Git, GitLab, GitHub Actions, Jenkins, Kubernetes, CircleCI

**Cloud Infrastructure** Terraform, Cloudformation, CDK, Pulumi

**Tools:** 

Streaming: Apache Kafka, AWS Flink, Bytewax, CDC pattern, RabbitMQ, GCP pub/sub

ML Optimization TorchServe, TensorFlow Serving, Ray Serve, NVIDIA TensorRT-LLM, NVIDIA Triton

Inference Server, ollama, llama.cpp, vllm, sglang, LitServe, TGI, KV cache

Continuous batching, Speculative Decoding, FL(with ONNX)

## - Career Experience

# InsoftAI, FL, United State

#### Senior Machine Learning Engineer & Backend Developer

02/2023 - present

I led and developed powerful AI-Driven Platforms and ML projects, streaming business operations by integrating AI-driven systems capable of handling up to 90% of customer inquiries. Developed Support-nGen $^{\text{TM}}$ , a proprietary system designed to enhance customer service by efficiently managing FAQs, support tickets, and complex queries.

Also, I developed a LLM Twin, an advanced AI character that emulates individual writing/coding styles, voices, and personalities to serve as an effective writing co-pilot, facilitating brand creation by automating the writing process, generating new creative ideas, and streamlining content creation.

- ☑ Implemented expertise in implementing a sequential request processing system with a strong emphasis on low latency, adopting an online real-time inference deployment architecture to enhance overall performance and responsiveness.
- ☑ Designed cloud-service/microservice architecture by splitting the ML service into a REST API server for business logic and an optimized LLM microservice, leveraging powerful machines and various engines to enhance latency and memory usage, thereby facilitating quick adaptation of the infrastructure based on different LLM sizes.
- ☑ Demonstrated a comprehensive approach by integrating Graph RAG with Neo4j within the business microservice, incorporating advanced RAG techniques to optimize the pre-retrieval, retrieval, and post-retrieval steps, resulting in enhanced accuracy and improved response, implementing binay quantization solution improving RAG search to 40x faster.
- ☑ Implemented a highly efficient deployment strategy for the LLM microservice on AWS SageMaker, utilizing Hugging Face's Deep Learning Containers (DLCs) to enhance model inference. This robust infrastructure supported scalable, secure, and efficient real-time predictions through critical components such as SageMaker endpoints, model configuration, and inference components. By leveraging the Text Generation Inference (TGI) engine, the system achieved superior computational efficiency via tensor and dynamic batching for leading open-source LLMs like Mistral, Llama, and Falcon, accomplished optimizing performance with flash-attention, minimizing model size through model parallelism and weight quantization, enhancing throughput with speculative decoding, continuous batching, accelerating weight loading using safetensors, and enabling real-time interactions via token streaming, culminating in a responsive and effective LLM serving solution and achieving speedups of 2-4x or more.
- ☑ Developed and implemented fine-tuning process with Unsloth, a high-performance library, utilizing custom kernels, accelerating training by 2-5x and significantly reducing memory usage by up to 80%.
- ☑ Engineered a business microservice using FastAPI, initially deployed to AWS Elastic Kubernetes Service (EKS) or AWS Elastic Container Service (ECS), involving Dockerization of the application, pushing the Docker image to AWS ECR, and configuring the deployment, while also orchestrating ML pipelines using ZenML / Airflow, storing and versioning ML pipelines as outputs, and attaching metadata to artifacts for better observability.
- ☑ Utilized advanced profiling tools to identify costly lines of code and uncover performance blind spots in local programs and Kubernetes clusters running on Linux, successfully optimizing CPU, GPU, and I/O performance, which led to an estimated 20% reduction in infrastructure costs.
- ☑ By integrating Ragas's strengths in production monitoring and LLM-assisted metrics with ARES's configurable evaluation process and classifier-based assessments, enhanced evaluation capabilities, achieving quick iterations and in-depth, customized evaluations that significantly improve performance outcomes.
- ☑ Designed a clean backend–frontend architecture with FastAPI, built a web API using FastAPI and add WebSocket support agent can respond in real time.
- ☑ Exhibited strong leadership abilities by mentoring junior staff, enhancing their communication skills, and encouraging professional development.

#### Brainhub, Gliwice, Poland

# AI/MLOps Engineer & Agent Developer

10/2019 - 12/2022

I developed Sierra.ai which redefines how businesses interact with data by simplifying document management and information accessibility. Sierra's customer-centric approach establishes it as a trusted and secure partner for businesses of all sizes looking to implement multi-agent systems with langchain, langGraph and langSmith for mornitoring.

Also, I engineered a real-time personalized recommender system for H&M fashion articles using the 4-stage recommender architecture and a two-tower model design architecture, leveraging the Hopsworks AI Lakehouse.

- ☑ I was responsible for the development of Sierra.ai, revolutionizing document management and information accessibility for businesses, resulting in a 30% increase in operational efficiency for clients, applied extensive knowledge in AI/ML research to design and implement advanced algorithms, enhancing the platform's capability to process and analyze complex data sets effectively.
- ☑ Led the formulation and execution of technical strategies that align with business goals, contributing to a 25% growth in user adoption rates over the past year, designed and optimized multi-AI agents capable of autonomous decision-making, which improved response times by 40% and reduced manual intervention needs.
- ☑ Designed and implemented three core ML serving architectures: online real-time inference, asynchronous inference, and offline batch transform. Balanced trade-offs between low latency and high throughput to optimize user experience

and meet deployment requirements for throughput, latency, data, and infrastructure.

- ☑ I designed and implemented a modular Python package that orchestrates the ML workflow into three fully automated real-time pipelines—feature, training, and inference—while reducing processing time by 62.5% preserving the accuracy or quality.
- $\ensuremath{\square}$  By addressing the limitations of traditional RAG with KAG, achieved over 94% accuracy in popular science queries and 93% in interpreting medical indicators, showed similarly impressive results, with precision rates of 91.6% and recall rates of 71.8% a significant improvement over traditional RAG methods.
- ☑ I adopted MLOps best practices, including Infrastructure as Code (IaC), CI/CD, monitoring, experiment tracking, and model registries, ensuring the system is reproducible, testable, and trackable and deployed a scalable and cost-effective asynchronous batch architecture on AWS ECS and SQS, dynamically scaling based on job volume and achieving a 52% reduction in AWS costs.
- ☑ Designed 4-stage architecture to build a system that can handle recommendations from a catalog of millions of items and two-tower model, a flexible neural network design that creates embeddings for users and items and optimized deploying ML models using Auto scaling, model optimization/parallelism/quantization, implementing a strategy similar to what TikTok employs for short videos, which will be applied to H&M retail items.
- ☑ Enhanced recommender systems by integrating advanced evaluation metrics such as NDCG, Precision@K, Recall@K, and Mean Reciprocal Rank (MRR), providing nuanced insights into model performance and user relevance, ultimately improving user satisfaction and engagement.
- ☑ Deployed real-time recommendations using Hopsworks Serverless and KServe, a runtime engine for serving predictive and generative ML models on Kubernetes, which simplifies autoscaling, networking, health checks, and server configuration while providing advanced features like GPU autoscaling and canary rollouts; through KServe, I successfully implemented two distinct services—the query encoder service and the ranking service—resulting in improved model performance and responsiveness in production.

## Kensho, Massachusetts, United State

#### Backend-heavy AI Developer, TTS/STT Multi-Modal Engineer

09/2016 - 09/2019

I worked on a TTS and STT solution, exposing it as an API that accurately clone voices from a short audio clip, significantly enhancing user experience in voice synthesis applications and built an ML system for forecasting hourly energy consumption levels across Denmark, improving predictive accuracy and operational planning.

- ☑ I built an inference pipleline in LangChain as a serverless RESTful API, enabling real-time financial question answering using RAG/TAG, significantly improving user engagement.
- ☑ Extended Meta's Llama 3 model with multimodal projector, allowing direct audio input for faster responses compared to traditional ASR-LLM combinations, enhancing system efficiency.
- ☑ I evaluated the team projects and dedicated time to mentoring junior developers, fostering skill development and enhancing team performance.
- ☑ Implemented on a advanced RAG agent that ingest document context and provide assistant-like answers, improving user queries resolution.
- ☑ Designed real-time streaming pipeline for monitoring financial news, processing documents, and storing them in a vector database, enhancing data retrieval efficiency.
- ☑ Developed a serverless continuous training solution that fine-tunes an LLM on financial data, optimizing model performance through automatic tracking and registry saving.
- ☑ Built efficient batch prediction pipelines using Python, leveraing a Feature Store and GCS, orchestrated with Airflow, resulting in streamlined predictions and improved operational workflows.

## Dana Scott Design, Indianapolis, United States

#### Full Stack Developer/assistant

02/2014 - 8/2016

- $\ensuremath{\square}$  Started a career as a front-end developer and move to full stack position.
- ☑ Translated Figma designs into user-friendly, reusable React components with high productivity and responsibility by leveraging proficiency in HTML/CSS and React-styled components.
- ☑ Designed and implemented RESTful APIs, optimizing communication and dataflow for enhanced application functionality.

#### - Education

Bachelor Degree in Computer Science

University of Kansas (2009 – 2013)

Bobby Estes – Page 3 | 3